

ABOUT ME

I am keen to explore different spaces of the built environment and use my multidisciplinary experience as a mechanical engineer and data practitioner to understand our dynamic reality with its inherent complexity. I am interested in the use of design and data science to influence the processes that govern human systems like education, health, water, energy and food.

SKILLS

- Data processing, analysis and visualization: SAS, R, Python, Processing
- Computer aided design: Autodesk, Pro E
- Business intelligence: Tableau, Qlikview
- Music production
- Writing
- Movement teacher and practitioner: Acroyoga, Equilibre, Calisthenics

SAKSHAM KAPOOR

saksham.kapoor@anu.edu.in III-D/53, Nehru Nagar, Ghaziabad, Uttar Pradesh-201001 +91-8197924637

EXPERIENCE

CIVIL SERVICES EXAMINATION, APRIL 2015- JUNE 2018

Worked on developing an understanding of the multidisciplinary facets of the world ranging from history, polity, environment, sociology etc to gain a more holistic perspective of our lived reality. The knowledge gained through this process has provided a framework to decipher the complexity of our global order and its shortcomings and be better equipped to create sustainable solutions.

TRAINEE DECISION SCIENTIST, MU SIGMA BUSINESS SOLUTIONS PUT LTD — AUGUST, 2013- APRIL 2015

Led a team responsible for creating business intelligence tools related to marketing related data for a pharmaceutical client. The work included data management, processing as well as visualizations well as creating automation tools for data validation. Also worked on creating a repository of business problems from various verticals including technology, aviation, education, marketing etc and creating a framework for data driven solutions with the help of research and causal inference.

INTERN, MARUTI SUZUKI PVT LTD — JANUARY-JUNE 2012

Worked in the body design department in the engineering devision of the Gurgaon plant. Involved with designing a methodology and fabricating a contraption to quantify the A pillar obstruction in several car models. Also worked on topography optimization of the roof of various models to reduce the weight and cost while still maintaining regulated strength and crash standards.

INTERN, ANEST IWATA MOTHERSON — DECEMBER 2009- JANUARY 2010

Worked in the manufacturing division and successfully implemented cycle time reduction for a cylinder block in the CNC lathe by optimizing processes and bringing in new tool bits in the production procedure.

EDUCATION

PGDM IN THE BUILT ENVIRONMENT, ANANT FELLOWSHIP, SEPTEMBER 2018- PRESENT BE MECHANICAL ENGINEERING, THAPAR UNIVERITY, PATIALA - JUNE 2009- JUNE 2013 CLASS 12 CBSE BOARD, 2009-DELHI PUBLIC SCHOOL GHAZIABAD, GHAZIABAD: 92.6% CLASS 10 CBSE BOARD, 2007-DELHI PUBLIC SCHOOL GHAZIABAD, GHAZIABAD: 93%

INTERESTS

ASSISTANT TO MS. ALLENA HUMSTOE (ACROVINYASA TEACHER)- DECEMBER 2017-SEPTEMBER 2018

Assisted Ms. Humstoe in conducting multiple Acrovinyasa workshops in NCR. It is a physical movement form which imbibes characteristics of acrobatics, vinyasa yoga and thai massage.

MUSIC PRODUCTION

Created the background score and worked extensively through the development stage of two gaming applications for Android and iOS smartphones(Emojiblitz and AsteroidDestroy) for Global Online Corporation. Have been involved with music production and performance for the last decade.